<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.30 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-trammell-plus-spec-00" category="exp">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="PLUS Spec">Path Layer UDP Substrate Specification</title>

    <author initials="B." surname="Trammell" fullname="Brian Trammell">
      <organization>ETH Zurich</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Gloriastrasse 35</street>
          <city>8092 Zurich</city>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ietf@trammell.ch</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Kuehlewind" fullname="Mirja Kuehlewind">
      <organization>ETH Zurich</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Gloriastrasse 35</street>
          <city>8092 Zurich</city>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mirja.kuehlewind@tik.ee.ethz.ch</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2016" month="December" day="23"/>

    
    
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This document specifies a common Path Layer UDP Substrate (PLUS) wire image
for encrypted transport protocols carried over UDP. The base PLUS header
carries information for driving a minimal state machine at middleboxes
described in <xref target="I-D.trammell-plus-statefulness"/>, and provides optional
exposure of additional information to devices along the path using the
mechanism described in <xref target="I-D.trammell-plus-abstract-mech"/>.</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>This document defines a wire image for a Path Layer UDP Substrate (PLUS), for
limited exposure of information from encrypted, UDP-encapsulated transport
protocols. The wire image implements signaling to drive the minimal state
machine defined in <xref target="I-D.trammell-plus-statefulness"/> as well as optional
exposure of additional information to devices along the path using the
mechanism described in <xref target="I-D.trammell-plus-abstract-mech"/>.</t>

<t>As discussed in <xref target="I-D.hardie-path-signals"/>, basic information about flows
currently exposed by TCP are missing from transport protocols that encrypt
their headers. Given the ossification of protocol wire images due to the
widespread deployment of stateful network devices that rely on header
inspection, this header encryption is necessary to support transport protocol
evolution. However, the loss of basic information for on-path state
maintenance as well as network performance measurement, diagnostics, and
troubleshooting via header encryption makes network management more difficult.
The PLUS wire image defined by this document aims to mitigate this difficulty,
allowing deployment of encrypted protocols without loss of essential in-
network functionality.</t>

<t>This wire image is intended primarily to support state maintenance and
measurement; the principles of measurement and primitives we aim to support
are drawn from recent work on explicit measurability in protocol design
<xref target="IPIM"/>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="basic-header" title="State Maintenance and Measurement: Basic Header">

<t>Every packet in each direction of a flow using PLUS MUST carry either a PLUS
basic or PLUS extended header. The PLUS basic header supports multiplexing
using a connection token; basic state maintenance using association and
confirmation signals, packet serial numbers, and a two-way stop signal; and
basic measurability using packet serial number echo. The format of the basic
header, together with the UDP header, is shown in <xref target="fig-header-basic"/>.</t>

<t>The extended header is defined in <xref target="extended-header"/>.</t>

<figure title="PLUS header with basic exposure" anchor="fig-header-basic"><artwork><![CDATA[
  3                   2                   1
1 0 9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0 9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0 9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0
+------------------------------+-------------------------------+
|       UDP source port        |      UDP destination port     |
+------------------------------+-------------------------------+
|       UDP length             |      UDP checksum             |
+------------------------------+-------------------------------+
|                            magic                             |
+--------------------------------------------------------------+
|                                                              |
+-             connection/association token CAT               -+
|                                                              |
+--------------------------------------------------------------+
|                 packet serial number  PSN                    |
+--------------------------------------------------------------+
|                 packet serial echo    PSE                    |
+-+-+-+-+-------+-----------------------------------------------+
|S|0|L|R|  ign  |                                              \
+-+-+-+-+-------+                                              /
/                                                              \
\         transport protocol header/payload (encrypted)        /
/                                                              \
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Fields are encoded in network byte order and are defined as follows:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>magic: A 32-bit number identifying this packet as carrying a PLUS header.
This magic number is chosen to avoid collision with possible values of the
first four bytes of widely deployed protocols on UDP. Should the QUIC 
<xref target="I-D.ietf-quic-transport"/> header be defined to place the version number
in the first four bytes of the packet, this number should be compatible with
the QUIC version numbering scheme. The value 0xd8007ffe has been 
provisionally selected for the PLUS magic number based of experience with 
the SPUD prototype, and a cursory survey of common UDP protocols.</t>
  <t>Connection/Association Token (CAT): A 64-bit token identifying this 
association. The CAT should be chosen randomly by the connection initiator. 
The CAT performs two functions in the PLUS header:  <list style="symbols">
      <t>Multiplexing: PLUS packets on the same 5-tuple with a different CAT value 
are taken to belong to a separate flow, with completely separate
state.</t>
      <t>Rebinding: A PLUS packet sharing one endpoint (source address/port 
pair, or destination address/port pair) and the CAT with an existing 
flow is taken to belong to that flow, since the other endpoint 
identifier has changed due to a mobility event or address translation 
change.</t>
    </list></t>
  <t>Packet Serial Number (PSN): A 32-bit serial number for this packet. The
first PSN for each direction in a flow is chosen randomly, and subsequent
packets increment the PSN by one. The PSN wraps around.</t>
  <t>Packet Serial Echo (PSE): The most recent PSN seen by the
sender in the opposite direction before this packet was sent.</t>
  <t>Flags byte: eight bits carrying additional flags:  <list style="symbols">
      <t>Stop flag (S): Packet carries a stop or stop confirmation when set.</t>
      <t>Extended Header bit: Flag bit 0x40 is set to zero in packets with a Basic Header.</t>
      <t>LoLa flag (L): Packet is latency sensitive and prefers drop to delay when set.</t>
      <t>RoI flag (R): Packet is not sensitive to reordering when set.</t>
      <t>Ignored: Bits 0-3 are ignored, and available for use by the overlying transport.</t>
    </list></t>
</list></t>

<t>Since PLUS is designed to be used for UDP-encapsulated, encrypted transport
protocols, overlying transports are presumed to provide encryption and
integrity protection for their own headers. For the sake of efficiency, it is
also assumed that this integrity protection can be extended to the bits in the
PLUS Basic Header.</t>

<section anchor="sender-behavior" title="Sender Behavior">

<t>When a sender has a packet ready to send using PLUS, it determines the values
in the Basic Header as follows:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>The magic number is set to the constant 0xd8007ffe.</t>
  <t>If the sender is the flow initiator, and the packet is the first packet in
the flow, the sender selects a cryptographically random 64-bit number for
the CAT. When multiplexing, it must ensure the PSN is not already in use for
the 5-tuple. Otherwise, the sender uses the CAT associated with the flow.</t>
  <t>If the packet is the first packet in the flow in this direction, the sender
selects a cryptographically random 32-bit number for the PSN. Otherwise, the
sender adds one to the PSN on the last packet it sent in this flow, and uses
that value for the PSN. If the last PSN is 0xffffffff, it wraps around,
setting the PSN to 0x00000000.</t>
  <t>If the packet is the first packet in the flow in this direction, the sender
sets the PSE to 0x00000000. Otherwise it sets the PSE to the PSN of the last
packet seen in the opposite direction.</t>
  <t>If the overlying transport determines that this packet is the last to be
 sent in this direction, the sender sets the S flag; see
 <xref target="bidirectional-stop-signaling"/> for details.</t>
  <t>If the overlying transport determines that this packet is loss-insensitive
but latency-sensitive, the sender sets the L flag.</t>
  <t>If the overlying transport determines that this packet may be freely
reordered, the sender sets the R flag.</t>
  <t>The overlying transport may freely use the four ignored flag bits for its
own purposes.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="receiver-behavior" title="Receiver Behavior">

<t>When a receiver receives a packet containing a PLUS Basic Header, it processes
the values in the Basic Header as follows:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>It verifies that the magic number is the constant 0xd800fffe.</t>
  <t>It verifies the integrity of the information in the PLUS Basic Header, using
information carried in the overlying transport. Packets failing integrity
checks SHOULD be dropped, but MAY be further analyzed by the receiver to
determine the likely cause of verification failure; reaction to the failure is
transport and implementation specific.</t>
  <t>It stores the PSN to be sent as the PSE on the the next packet it sends in
the opposite direction.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="on-path-state-maintenance-using-the-basic-header" title="On-Path State Maintenance using the Basic Header">

<t>The basic header provides all the signals necessary to drive the transport-
independent state machine described in <xref target="I-D.trammell-plus-statefulness"/>, as
shown in <xref target="fig-states"/>.</t>

<figure title="Transport-independent state machine as implemented by PLUS" anchor="fig-states"><artwork><![CDATA[
    `- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -'
    `    +============+    a->b    +============+           '
    `   /              \--------->/              \<-+       '
  +--->(      zero      )        (    uniflow     ) | a->b  '
  ^ `   \              /<---------\              /--+       '
  | `    +============+  TO_IDLE   +============+           '
  | `- - - - - - - - - - - - - - -  | b->a - - - - - - - - -'
  |                                 V
  |                          +============+  
  | TO_IDLE                 /              \ 
  +<-----------------------(  associating   )
  |                         \              / 
  |                          +============+  
  |                                 | a->b
  |                                 V       
  |                          +============+ 
  | TO_ASSOCIATED           /              \<-+     
  +<-----------------------(   associated   ) | a<->b
  |                         \              /--+     
  |                          +============+ 
  |                             | stop y->z   
  |                             V             
  |                    +============+  
  | TO_ASSOCIATED     /              \<-+     
  +<-----------------(   half-close   ) | a<->b
  |                   \              /--+          
  |                   +============+       
  |                       | stop z->y
  |                       V
  |              +============+
  | TO_CLOSING  /              \
  +------------(    closing     )
                \              /
                 +============+
]]></artwork></figure>

<section anchor="state-establishment" title="State Establishment">

<t>A PLUS-aware on-path device forwarding a packet with a PLUS Basic Header with
a 5-tuple and CAT it does not have state for moves that flow to the uniflow
state. It will move the flow back to zero state after not seeing a packet on
the same flow in the same direction with the same CAT within a timeout
interval TO_IDLE, and continues forwarding packets in that direction (the a-&gt;b
direction in <xref target="fig-states"/>).</t>

<t>A PLUS-aware on-path device forwarding a packet with a PLUS Basic Header with
a matching 5-tuple and CAT as a flow in the uniflow state, but in the opposite
direction (the b-&gt;a direction in <xref target="fig-states"/>), moves that flow to the
associating state. It stores the PSN of the packet that caused this
transition, and waits for a packet in the a-&gt;b direction containing a PSE
indicating that that packet has been received. When it sees that packet, it
transitions the flow to associated state. Otherwise, it drops state after a
timeout interval TO_IDLE.</t>

<t>Once a flow has moved to the associated state, it will remain in that state
for a timeout interval TO_ASSOCIATED. The on-path device forwards any packet
with a PLUS Basic Header in either direction for this flow. It resets the
TO_ASSOCIATED timer for every packet it forwards in this state.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="bidirectional-stop-signaling" title="Bidirectional Stop Signaling">

<t>A PLUS-aware on-path device forwarding a packet for a flow in the associated
state with an S flag set moves that flow to half-close state. It stores the
PSN on the packet causing the transition, and continues forwarding packets as
if in associated state, dropping state on timeout interval TO_ASSOCIATED.</t>

<t>When it sees a packet in the opposite direction with the S flag set and the
PSE set to exactly the stored PSN, it transitions the flow to closing state.
The device will forward packets in both directions for flows in the closing
state within a timeout interval TO_CLOSING; these packets will not reset the
timer. See <xref target="bidirectional-stop-signaling"/> for details.</t>

<t>Note that even though the S flag is integrity-protected end to end, a packet
with the S flag set could be forged by one on-path device to drive the flow
into half-close state on all downstream devices. However, this attack is of
severely limited utility. First, it would require coordination between
attackers on both sides of a given on-path device in order to forge a
confirmation of the stop signal – a flag with the S bit set and a valid PSE
corresponding to the PSN of the first stop signal to drive the flow into
closing state. Second, the information in the Basic Header on each packet will
drive the state machine into associated state even in the middle of a flow,
enabling fast recovery even in the case of such a coordinated attack.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="state-rebinding" title="State Rebinding">

<t>A PLUS-aware on-path device forwarding a packet for a flow in the zero state,
where one of the endpoint identifiers (address and port) and the CAT, but not
the other endpoint identifier, match a flow in a non-zero state, accounts that
packet to the existing flow, updating the changed endpoint identifier. This
allows fast rebinding of state in case of changes in network address
translation or connectivity of the sender.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="measurement-and-diagnosis-using-the-basic-header" title="Measurement and Diagnosis using the Basic Header">

<t>The basic header trivially supports passive two-way delay measurement as well
as partial loss estimation at a single observation point.</t>

<t>To calculate two-way delay, an observation point calculates the delay between
seeing a PSN and a corresponding PSE in each direction, then adds the delays
from each direction together. The fact that the PSN increments by one for
every packet, including packets carrying retransmitted data or only control
traffic, makes this measurement much simpler than the equivalent measurement
using TCP sequence and acknowledgment numbers.</t>

<t>To calculate loss upstream from an observation point in each direction, the
observation point simply counts skips in the PSN number space. Since PLUS does
not expose information about retransmissions (and, indeed, may not even carry
a transport that uses retransmission for loss recovery), loss downstream from
the observation point cannot be observed.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="extended-header" title="Path Communication: Extended Header">

<t>Additional facilities for communicating with on-path devices under endpoint
control are provided by the PLUS Extended Header. The extended header shares
the layout of its first 21 bytes with the PLUS Basic Header, except the
Extended Header bit (0x40 on byte 20) is set. As with the Basic Header,
overlying transports are presumed to provide encryption and integrity
protection for the PLUS Extended Header.</t>

<t>The Extended Header shown in <xref target="fig-header-pcf"/> provides for a single Sender
to Path or Path to Receiver information element, as in 
<xref target="I-D.trammell-plus-abstract-mech"/>, to appear on the packet, 
within a Path Communication Field.
PCF Type information is carried in Byte 21 of the header, with the length of
the PCF value to be determined by its type.</t>

<t>Further details of PCF encoding are not yet defined in this revision of the
specification; the remainder of this section discusses the types of
information elements to be supported. The exact encoding of PCF type and value
information are to be derived from an analysis of the requirements of these
Information Elements.</t>

<figure title="PLUS extended header (conceptual; details TBD)" anchor="fig-header-pcf"><artwork><![CDATA[
  3                   2                   1
1 0 9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0 9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0 9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1 0
+------------------------------+-------------------------------+
|       UDP source port        |      UDP destination port     |
+------------------------------+-------------------------------+
|       UDP length             |      UDP checksum             |
+------------------------------+-------------------------------+
|                            magic                             |
+--------------------------------------------------------------+
|                                                              |
+-             connection/association token CAT               -+
|                                                              |
+--------------------------------------------------------------+
|                 packet serial number  PSN                    |
+--------------------------------------------------------------+
|                 packet serial echo    PSE                    |
+-+-+-+-+-------+---------------+------------------------------+
|S|1|L|R|  ign  |    PCF Type   |                              /
+-+-+-+-+-------+---------------+                              \
\                                                              /
/                 PCF value (variable-length)                  \
\                                                              /
+--------------------------------------------------------------+
/                                                              \
\         transport protocol header/payload (encrypted)        /
/                                                              \
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>As described in <xref target="I-D.trammell-plus-abstract-mech"/>, there are two types of
signals: Path to Receiver signals, which allow devices along the path to
provide information about the path or its treatment of the flow to the
receiver; and Sender to Path signals, which allow the sender to expose
information about itself or the flow to the path. Path to Receiver signals are
treated specially by header integrity protection, as their values, but not
length or type, may be changed by devices on path: the value of a given path-
to-receiver signal is assumed to be an appropriately sized array of zero bytes
by the integrity protection facility.</t>

<t>Path to Receiver signals generally take the form of accumulators: initialized
to some value by the sender, and subject to some aggregation function by each
on-path device that understands them. Sender to Path signals are generally
used to expose information about the traffic for measurement or diagnostic
purposes. In any case, the information sent and received is to be treated as
advisory only.</t>

<section anchor="measurement-and-diagnostics-using-the-extended-header" title="Measurement and Diagnostics using the Extended Header">

<t>We have identified the following sender to path signals as potentially useful
for measurement and diagnostic purposes. These signals are advisory only, and
should not be presumed by either the endpoints or devices along the path to
affect forwarding behavior.</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Timestamp and timestamp echo. Similar to TCP timestamps in <xref target="RFC7323"/>, also
encoding a delta between receipt of last timestamp and transmission of echo
as in section 4.1.2 of <xref target="IPIM"/>. Allows constant-rate clock exposure to devices
on path. Note that this is less necessary for RTT measurement of one-sided flows 
than it is in TCP, due to the properties of the PSN and PSE values in the Basic Header.</t>
</list></t>

<t>We have identified the following path to receiver signals as potentially
useful. Note that accumulated values for use at the sender must be fed back to
the sender by the overlying transport, and that the presence of non-PLUS aware
devices on path at breaks in MTU mean that the accumulated value can only be
used as a hint to processes for measurement and discovery of the accumulated
values at the sender.</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>MTU accumulator. This signal allows measurement of MTU information from
PLUS-aware devices. The sender sets the initial value to the sender’s MTU. A
PLUS-aware forwarding device on path receiving this value fills in the
minimum of the received value and the MTU of the next hop into this field.</t>
  <t>State timeout accumulator. This signal allows measurement of timeouts
from PLUS-aware devices. It is initialized to a maximum (“no information”)
value by the sender. A PLUS-aware forwarding device on path receiving this
value fills in the minimum of the received value and the configured timeout
for the flow’s present state into this field.</t>
  <t>Rate limit accumulator. This signal allows exposure of rate limiting
along the path. It is initialized to a maximum (“no information”) value by
the sender. A PLUS-aware forwarding device on path receiving this value
fills in the minimum of the received value and the rate limit to which this 
flow is subject into this field.</t>
  <t>Trace accumulator. This signal allows exposure of a trace of PLUS-aware
devices on path, similar to the Path Changes mechanism in section 4.3 of
<xref target="IPIM"/>. The sender initializes the value to a value chosen randomly for the
flow; all packets in the flow using path trace accumulator must use the same
initial value. A PLUS-aware forwarding device on path receiving this value
fills in the result of XORing the received value with a randomly chosen device
identifier, which it must use for all path trace accumulator signals it
participates in. Packets traversing the same set of PLUS-aware forwarding
devices in the same flow therefore arrive at the receiver with the same
accumulated value, and changes to the set of devices on path can be detected
by the receiver.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This document has no actions for IANA. Path communication field types and PLUS
magic numbers may be moved to a Standards Action registry in a future
revision.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>[EDITOR’S NOTE: write me]</t>

</section>
<section anchor="acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">

<t>This work is partially supported by the European Commission under Horizon 2020
grant agreement no. 688421 Measurement and Architecture for a Middleboxed
Internet (MAMI), and by the Swiss State Secretariat for Education, Research,
and Innovation under contract no. 15.0268. This support does not imply
endorsement.</t>

</section>


  </middle>

  <back>


    <references title='Informative References'>





<reference  anchor='RFC0793' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc793'>
<front>
<title>Transmission Control Protocol</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Postel' fullname='J. Postel'><organization /></author>
<date year='1981' month='September' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='7'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='793'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC0793'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC2474' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2474'>
<front>
<title>Definition of the Differentiated Services Field (DS Field) in the IPv4 and IPv6 Headers</title>
<author initials='K.' surname='Nichols' fullname='K. Nichols'><organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Blake' fullname='S. Blake'><organization /></author>
<author initials='F.' surname='Baker' fullname='F. Baker'><organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Black' fullname='D. Black'><organization /></author>
<date year='1998' month='December' />
<abstract><t>This document defines the IP header field, called the DS (for differentiated services) field.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2474'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2474'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC7675' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7675'>
<front>
<title>Session Traversal Utilities for NAT (STUN) Usage for Consent Freshness</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Perumal' fullname='M. Perumal'><organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Wing' fullname='D. Wing'><organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Ravindranath' fullname='R. Ravindranath'><organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Reddy' fullname='T. Reddy'><organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Thomson' fullname='M. Thomson'><organization /></author>
<date year='2015' month='October' />
<abstract><t>To prevent WebRTC applications, such as browsers, from launching attacks by sending traffic to unwilling victims, periodic consent to send needs to be obtained from remote endpoints.</t><t>This document describes a consent mechanism using a new Session Traversal Utilities for NAT (STUN) usage.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7675'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7675'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC7323' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7323'>
<front>
<title>TCP Extensions for High Performance</title>
<author initials='D.' surname='Borman' fullname='D. Borman'><organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Braden' fullname='B. Braden'><organization /></author>
<author initials='V.' surname='Jacobson' fullname='V. Jacobson'><organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Scheffenegger' fullname='R. Scheffenegger' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<date year='2014' month='September' />
<abstract><t>This document specifies a set of TCP extensions to improve performance over paths with a large bandwidth * delay product and to provide reliable operation over very high-speed paths.  It defines the TCP Window Scale (WS) option and the TCP Timestamps (TS) option and their semantics.  The Window Scale option is used to support larger receive windows, while the Timestamps option can be used for at least two distinct mechanisms, Protection Against Wrapped Sequences (PAWS) and Round-Trip Time Measurement (RTTM), that are also described herein.</t><t>This document obsoletes RFC 1323 and describes changes from it.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7323'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7323'/>
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.hardie-path-signals'>
<front>
<title>Path signals</title>

<author initials='T' surname='Hardie' fullname='Ted Hardie'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' day='28' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>TCP's state mechanics uses a series of well-known messages that are exchanged in the clear.  Because these are visible to network elements on the path between the two nodes setting up the transport connection, they are often used as signals by those network elements. In transports that do not exchange these messages in the clear, on- path network elements lack those signals.  This document discusses the nature of the signals as they are seen by on-path elements and reflects on best practices for transports which encrypt their state mechanics.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-hardie-path-signals-00' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-hardie-path-signals-00.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.trammell-plus-abstract-mech'>
<front>
<title>Abstract Mechanisms for a Cooperative Path Layer under Endpoint Control</title>

<author initials='B' surname='Trammell' fullname='Brian Trammell'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='September' day='28' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>draft-trammell-plus-abstract-mech-00  Abstract  This document describes the operation of three abstract mechanisms for supporting an explicitly cooperative path layer in the Internet architecture.  Three mechanisms are described: sender to path signaling with receiver integrity verification; path to receiver signaling with confidential feedback to sender; and direct path to sender signaling.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-trammell-plus-abstract-mech-00' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-trammell-plus-abstract-mech-00.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.trammell-plus-statefulness'>
<front>
<title>Transport-Independent Path Layer State Management</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Kuehlewind' fullname='Mirja Kuehlewind'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Trammell' fullname='Brian Trammell'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Hildebrand' fullname='Joe Hildebrand'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='December' day='22' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>This document describes a simple state machine for stateful network devices on a path between two endpoints to associate state with traffic traversing them on a per-flow basis, as well as abstract signaling mechanisms for driving the state machine.  This state machine is intended to replace the de-facto use of the TCP state machine or incomplete forms thereof by stateful network devices in a transport-independent way, while still allowing for fast state timeout of non-established or undesirable flows.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-trammell-plus-statefulness-02' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-trammell-plus-statefulness-02.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-quic-transport'>
<front>
<title>QUIC: A UDP-Based Multiplexed and Secure Transport</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Iyengar' fullname='Janardhan Iyengar'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Thomson' fullname='Martin Thomson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='November' day='28' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>QUIC is a multiplexed and secure transport protocol that runs on top of UDP.  QUIC builds on past transport experience, and implements mechanisms that make it useful as a modern general-purpose transport protocol.  Using UDP as the basis of QUIC is intended to address compatibility issues with legacy clients and middleboxes.  QUIC authenticates all of its headers, preventing third parties from from changing them.  QUIC encrypts most of its headers, thereby limiting protocol evolution to QUIC endpoints only.  Therefore, middleboxes, in large part, are not required to be updated as new protocol versions are deployed.  This document describes the core QUIC protocol, including the conceptual design, wire format, and mechanisms of the QUIC protocol for connection establishment, stream multiplexing, stream and connection-level flow control, and data reliability.  Accompanying documents describe QUIC's loss recovery and congestion control, and the use of TLS 1.3 for key negotiation.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-quic-transport-00' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-quic-transport-00.txt' />
</reference>


<reference anchor="IPIM" >
  <front>
    <title>In-Protocol Internet Measurement (arXiv preprint 1612.02902)</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Allman">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Beverly">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Trammell">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016" month="December" day="09"/>
  </front>
</reference>


    </references>



  </back>
</rfc>

